<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
		which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
		There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
		An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2629 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3236 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3236.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3864 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3864.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3870 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3870.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5234 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5988 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5988.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6906 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6906.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7230 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7230.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7231 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7231.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7240 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7240.xml">

]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
		please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
		(Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
		(using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-svensson-accept-profile-00" ipr="trust200902">
	<!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

	<front>
		<!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
				full title is longer than 39 characters -->

		<title>Negotiating Profiles in HTTP</title>

		<author fullname="Lars G. Svensson" initials="L.G.S."
				surname="Svensson">
			<organization>Deutsche Nationalbibliothek</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>Adickesallee 1</street>
					<code>60322</code>
					<city>Frankfurt</city>
					<region/>
					<country>Germany</country>
				</postal>
				<phone>+49 69 1525 1752</phone>
				<email>l.svensson@dnb.de</email>
			</address>
		</author>

		<author fullname="Ruben Verborgh" initials="R.V."
				surname="Verborgh">
			<organization>Ghent University &#8211; imec</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>Sint-Pietersnieuwstraat 41</street>
					<code>9000</code>
					<city>Ghent</city>
					<region/>
					<country>Belgium</country>
				</postal>
				<phone>+32 9 331 49 10</phone>
				<email>ruben.verborgh@ugent.be</email>
			</address>
		</author>

		<date year="2017" />

		<!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

		<area>General</area>

		<workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

		<!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
				IETF is fine for individual submissions.	
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
				which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

		<keyword>HTTP, Header, Content Negotiation</keyword>

		<abstract>
			<t>This document defines two new HTTP headers that enable User Agents
				and hosts to indicate and negotiate the profile
				used to represent a specific resource.
				In this context, a profile is a document describing the structural
				and/or semantic constraints of a group of documents
				in addition to the syntactical interpretation provided by a MIME type.
				Examples of profiles include Dublin Core Application Profiles, XML Schemata and 
				RDF Shape Expressions. Further, it defines and registers the profile
				parameter for the HTTP Link header and suggests a best practice for
				the use of the new headers together with the Link header to perform content
				negotiation and point clients to alternate representations.</t>
		</abstract>
	</front>

	<middle>
		<section title="Introduction">
			<t>This document defines two new HTTP headers that enable User Agents (UAs) and
				hosts to indicate and negotiate the profile used to represent a specific resource.
				On the Web, resources are identified with HTTP(S) URIs.
				In many cases, it can be desired to have multiple representations of a
				resource to accomodate different UAs or use cases.
				When a UA issues a GET request for a
				specific URI, the UA and the server negotiate which of the
				available representations best suit the UA's needs and capabilities. 
				Typically a UA specifies preferences by setting appropriate HTTP
				headers, e. g. Accept for media type, Accept-Language for content language
				or Accept-Charset for character encoding.</t>
			<t>In many cases, there are several ways to describe a resource
				within the scope of the media type.
				In the case of XML documents, for instance, the same content can be encoded
				using one of several DTDs or XML Schemas, whereas in RDF there is a wide
				choice of RDF vocabularies (classes and properties) available to describe
				resources of the same type.
				When a UA initiates a request, e.g., a GET request to retrieve
				or a PUT request to create or replace a resource, neither the UA nor the
				server have any possibility to exchange information on how the transmitted
				resource will be structured precisely. This document proposes a solution by
				defining the HTTP headers Accept-Profile and Profile.</t>

			<section title="Requirements Language">
				<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
					"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
					document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
							target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section title="Terminology and Implementation Options">
			<section title="A Note on Terminology">
				<t>In the context of this proposal, a "profile" is a document that expresses
					the structural and/or semantic constraints of other documents. Examples
					of "profile" in this context include, but are not limited to, Dublin Core 
					application profiles - formally expressed in 
					<xref target="DSP">Description Set Profiles (DSP)</xref>
					-, <xref target="XSD">XML Schema documents</xref> and RDF Shapes expressed in 
					<xref target="SHACL">SHACL</xref>. How those profiles are used by consuming applications is beyond the
					scope of this proposal, but typical use cases are validation of data
					received from another system and the automated creation of objects from
					received data as in <xref target="XMLBEANS">Java XMLBeans</xref>. The
					choice of the term "profile"was derived from the term "Application Profile"
					which the Dublin Core community defines as "schemas which consist of data
					elements drawn from one or more namespaces, combined together by implementors,
					and optimised for a particular local application" <xref target="rachelandheery">[Rachel &amp; Heery]</xref>.
				</t>
			</section>
			<section anchor="options_considered" title="Other Implementation Options Considered">
				<t>
					A number of options were considered when specifying how schema negotiation 
					could be implemented. Below is a record of those options listing the consequences
					of using them:
				</t>

				<t>
					<list style="numbers">
						<t>The HTTP "Link" header <xref target="RFC5988">[RFC 5988]</xref> offers various
						possibilities to relate a resource to other resources, e. g. to alternate representations
						having different media types or content in another language. One of the specified relationtypes
						is "profile" <xref target="RFC6906">[RFC 6906]</xref>, that offers the possibility to 
						associate a resource with a document describing "additional semantics that can be used to process a
						resource representation, such as constraints, conventions,
						extensions, or any other aspects that do not alter the basic media
						type semantics." This header can be used for a client to specify what profile it would
						the requested resource to conform to. This option offers no possibility to use q-values
						and thus does not allow the UA and the server to properly negotiate which profile to use.
						<figure align="center" anchor="rfc6906-example">
							<preamble>Example:</preamble>
							<artwork align="left">
HEAD /some/other/resource HTTP/1.1
Accept: text/turtle;q=0.9,application/rdf+xml;q=0.5
Link: &lt;http://example.com/profile-1&gt;; rel="profile"

HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-type: text/turtle
Link: &lt;http://example.com/profile-1&gt;; rel="profile"
							</artwork>
						</figure>
						</t>
						<t>Another way to use the Link" header directly, without using the "profile" relation.
						It is unclear if this usage
						can be applied in an http request, where the value of the link's context IRI is undefined 
						unless the client uses the "anchor" parameter to specify that, and even when the client 
						explicitly sets an anchor it is not specified if the relation between the anchor IRI and the
						related resource remains the same when a server redirects a client to another resource using e. g.
						the HTTP 301 or 303 status codes. This could be solved by letting the UA request a
						preferred profile by using the "Link" header together with the "profile" relation as described above and
						having the server specify which profile the returned resource conforms to and also
						link to alternate representations of the same resource. Currently, there is no target attribute 
						linking to a resource's profile. In order to enable this, this document registers the "profile"
						attribute to be used with the "Link" header.
						<figure align="center" anchor="rfc5988-example">
							<preamble>Example:</preamble>
							<artwork align="left">
GET some/resource HTTP/1.1
Accept: application/xml
Link: &lt;urn:example:schema-1&gt;; rel="profile"

HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: application/xml
Link: 	rel="self";
		type="application/xml"
		profile="&lt;urn:example:schema-1&gt;",
		rel="alternate";
		type="application/xml";
		profile="&lt;urn:example:schema-2&gt;
							</artwork>
						</figure>
						</t>

						<t>A further way to convey profile information is through the 
								http Accept and Content-Type header field as specified in <xref target="RFC7231">RFC 7231</xref>.
							<figure align="center" anchor="accept_with_profile">
								<preamble>Example:</preamble>
								<artwork align="left">
GET /some/resource HTTP/1.1
Accept: text/turtle;q=0.9;profile="urn:example:profile-1",
		text/turtle;q=0.7;profile="urn:example:profile-2";

HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: text/turtle;profile=&lt;urn:example:profile-2&gt;
								</artwork>
							</figure>
								If this is possible depends on the media 
								type. Of the media types commonly used for linked data, 
								only two registrations in the <xref target="IANAMEDIAREG">IANA Media Type Registry</xref>
								foresee the use of profiles: <xref target="RFC3236">application/xhtml+xml</xref>
								and <xref target="JSONLD">application/ld+json</xref>.
								E. g. neither <xref target="RFC3870">application/rdf+xml</xref> nor 
							<xref target="TURTLE">text/turtle</xref> do not
								mention the use of profiles.
						</t>
						<t>A fourth option would be to use the http "Prefer" and "Preference-Applied"
							headers as specified in <xref target="RFC7240">RFC 7240</xref>. This approach
							has two disadvantages. The first is - as with the "Link" header, that there
							is no possibility to work with q-values. The second one is that the only
							way for a server to state that it ignored the preference stated by the client
							is to omit sending a "Preference-Applied" header. For the client - however -
							it is not clear if the "Preference-Applied" header is absent because the server
							did not honour the preference, or if it is because the server did not understand
							the "Prefer" header in the first place. This could be solved by making it mandatory
							to send a "Link: rel=profile" header when answering to a request with a
							"Prefer: profile=''" header in it. This solution requires that a client evaluates
							two different headers in order to find a response to its request for a specific profile,
							which would make client implementation more complicated.
							<figure align="center" anchor="rfc7240-example">
								<preamble>Example:</preamble>
								<artwork align="left">
GET /some/resource HTTP/1.1
Accept: text/turtle
Prefer: profile=&lt;urn:example:schema&gt;

HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: text/turtle
Preference-Applied: profile=&lt;urn:example:schema&gt;
								</artwork>
							</figure>
						</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section title="Client and Server Behaviour">
			<t>The "Accept-Profile" and "Profile" header fields can be sent by both
				the UA and the server. The "Accept-Profile" header is used to specify
				one or more profiles the Agent can accept, whereas the "Profile" header tells
				the other Agent according to which profile the payload of the message is
				structured. So can a UA issuing a request for a resource specify that
				it prefers persons to be described using foaf, but that the BBC Core ontology 
				is also acceptable, and that it can only accept text/turtle, by setting the "Accept" and "Accept-Profile"
				header fields appropriately. When the server answers, it would set the 
				"Content-Type" and "Profile" header fields. Likewise, a UA sending an XML document to a server would set
				the the "Content-Type" and the "Profile" header fields. If the server cannot process the specified profile,
				it would answer with an http 406 status code and possibly a list of acceptable profiles.</t>
			<t>An "Accept-Profile" and "Profile" header field do not contain
				the actual profile but instead points to it using a URI. As long as the URI 
				is only used to denote the profile, the URI does not need to point to an
				actual document but can be considered opaque. If the parties involved 
				agree on a profile definition, the profile can be identified with e. g. a URN 
				or an info-URI. When a protocol-based URI, such as an FTP- or an HTTP-URI
				is used, however, it is RECOMMENDED that it dereference to a document containing
				the profile definition. 
			</t>
			<section title="Accept-Profile Header Syntax">
				<t>The "Accept-Profile" header field is used to specify one or more
					content profiles the issuing agent can accept for processing.
					Each profile is identified by a URI reference or -- e. g.
					in the case of namespace-specific XML schemas (cf. 
					<xref target="XMLSCHEMA">4.3.2 of XML Schema 1.1-1</xref>) -- a list of pairs of
					URI references separated by whitespace similar to the syntax used in the xsi:schemaLocation attribute.
					If several profiles are specified, quality values as defined in <xref target="RFC7230">Section 5.3.1 of
					RFC 7230</xref> can be used to assign a relative "weight" to the preference.
					Exactly how that weight is used to determine the best representation
					is beyond the scope of this specification.</t>
				<t>A request without any "Accept-Profile" header field implies that the user agent
					will accept content conforming to any profile. If the header field is
					present in a request and the origin server cannot provide a representation
					that conforms to the specified profile, it can either honour the header field by sending a 406 (Not
					Acceptable) response or disregard the header field by treating the
					response as if it is not subject to content negotiation. If the the origin server 
					chooses to disregard the header field and the profile the content conforms to is known,
					the origin server SHOULD send a "Profile" header indicating that profile
					together with the payload.</t>
				<t><xref target="abnf_accept_schema"/> describes the syntax (Augmented Backus-Naur Form) of the
					header fields, using the grammar defined in <xref target="RFC5234">RFC 5234</xref> and the rules
					defined in <xref target="RFC7230">Section 3.2 of RFC 7230</xref>.
					The definitions of "URI-reference" and "weight" are imported from
					<xref target="RFC7230">RFC 7230</xref> and <xref target="RFC7231">RFC 7231</xref>,
					respectively.</t>

				<figure align="center" anchor="abnf_accept_schema">
				<preamble>Accept-Profile header syntax</preamble>
					<artwork align="left" type="abnf">
Accept-Profile = "Accept-Profile" ":" (profile-value) *("," profile-value)
profile-value =  "&lt;" URI-reference "&gt;" [weight] |
                "&lt;" URI-reference "0x20" URI-reference
                        *("0x20" URI-reference "0x20" URI-reference) "&gt;"
						[weight]
					</artwork>
				</figure>
			</section>
			<section title="Profile Header Syntax">
				<t>The "Profile" header field is used to specify a profile the payload in the
					message conforms to. The profile is identified by a URI reference or -- e. g.
					in the case of namespace-specific XML schemas (cf. <xref target="XMLSCHEMA">4.3.2 
					of XML Schema 1.1-1</xref>) -- a list of pairs of URI references separated by
					whitespace similar to the syntax used in the xsi:schemaLocation attribute. If 
					a client uses the "Accept-Profile" header to specify one or more
					profiles it is willing to accept and a server does not use the "Profile" 
					header to specify which profile the returned content conforms to, 
					the client MAY process the returned content as it deems fit.</t>
				<t>If a client uses the "Profile" header field to indicate the profile the
					payload conforms to (e. g. in an HTTP POST or PUT request) and the
					server cannot process content conforming to that profile, the
					server SHOULD send a 406 (Not acceptable) response together with an "Accept-Profile"
					header field (including q-values) to indicate the profiles it 
					can process. Reasons for not sending a 406 response in such a case might be that
					the the processing of the message payload leads to an internal server error. If in
					such a case the server does not implement profile negotiation, the server is
					more likely to return a 500 (Internal server error) response instead of 406.</t>
				<t><xref target="abnf_schema"/> describes the syntax (Augmented Backus-Naur Form) of the
					header fields, using the grammar defined in <xref target="RFC5234">RFC 5234</xref> and the rules
					defined in <xref target="RFC7230">Section 3.2 of RFC 7230</xref>.
					The definition of "URI-reference" is imported from
					<xref target="RFC7230">RFC 7230</xref>.</t>
				<figure align="center" anchor="abnf_schema">
				<preamble>Profile header syntax</preamble>
					<artwork align="left" type="abnf">
Profile = "Profile" ":"  "&lt;" URI-reference "&gt;" |
                       "&lt;" URI-reference "0x20" URI-reference 
                       *( "0x20" URI-reference "0x20" URI-reference) "&gt;"
					</artwork>
				</figure>
			</section>

		</section>
		<section title="Examples">
			<t>The following examples highlight the exchange of profile information between a client
			and a server. For clarity, the examples only contain minimal information, i. e.
			only the relevant headers are included and message bodies are ignored.
				<figure align="left" anchor="example_1">
					<preamble>A client requests an XML document conforming to a specific XML schema.
					The XML schema is identified by "urn:example:schema:e-commerce-payment".</preamble>
					<artwork align="left">
Request:
GET /some-resource HTTP/1.1
Accept: application/xml
Accept-Profile: &lt;urn:example:schema:e-commerce-payment&gt;

Response:
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: application/xml
Profile: &lt;urn:example:schema:e-commerce-payment&gt;
Link: 	rel="self";
		type="application/xml";
		profile="&lt;urn:example:schema:e-commerce-payment&gt;",
		rel="alternate";
		type="application/xml";
		profile="&lt;urn:example:schema:e-commerce-accounting&gt;"
					</artwork>
				</figure>
				<figure align="left" anchor="example_2">
					<preamble>A client requests an RDF/XML document conforming to one of
					two RDF Shapes (http://example.com/shapes/shape-1 and http://example.com/shapes/shape-2).
					It uses q-values to express a preference for shape-1, the server, however,
					prefers to deliver in shape-2.</preamble>
					<artwork align="left">
Request:
GET /some-resource HTTP/1.1
Accept: application/rdf+xml
Accept-Profile: &lt;http://example.com/shapes/shape-1&gt;; q=0.8,
               &lt;http://example.com/shapes/shape-2&gt;; q=0.5

Response:
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: application/rdf+xml
Profile: &lt;http://example.com/shapes/shape-2&gt;
Link:	rel="self";
		type="application/rdf+xml";
		profile="&lt;http://example.com/shapes/shape-2&gt;",
		rel="alternate";
		type="application/rdf+xml";
		profile="&lt;http://example.com/shapes/shape-3&gt;"
					</artwork>
				</figure>
				<figure align="left" anchor="example_3">
					<preamble>A client PUTs a turtle document conforming to the RDF Shape
					http://example.com/shapes/shape-1. The server answers that it can only process
					documents conforming to http://example.com/shapes/shape-2.</preamble>
					<artwork align="left">
Request:
PUT /some-resource HTTP/1.1
Profile: &lt;http://example.com/shapes/shape-1&gt;

Response:
HTTP/1.1 406 Not acceptable
Content-Type: application/xhtml+xml
Accept-Profile: &lt;http://example.com/shapes/shape-2&gt;
					</artwork>
				</figure>
				<figure align="left" anchor="example_4">
					<preamble>A client requests an XML document where the elements in
					namespace urn:example:namespaces:ns1 must conform to XML schema http://example.com/schema/schema-1
					and the elements in namespace urn:example:namespaces:ns2 must conform to XML schema
					http://example.com/schema/schema-2. The server answers that it can supply the document as requested.</preamble>
					<artwork align="left">
Request:
GET /some-resource HTTP/1.1
Accept-Profile: 	&lt;urn:example:namespaces:ns1
				http://example.com/schema/schema-1
				urn:example:namespaces:ns2
				http://example.com/schema/schema-2&gt;

Response:
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: application/xml
Profile: &lt;urn:example:namespaces:ns1
		http://example.com/schema/schema-1
		urn:example:namespaces:ns2
		http://example.com/schema/schema-2&gt;
					</artwork>
				</figure>
			</t>

		</section>


		<section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
			<t>This is the place to have YOUR NAME prominently displayed!</t>

		</section>

		<!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

		<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
			<t>This specification defines two header field for the Hypertext
				Transfer Protocol (HTTP) that have been registered with the Internet
				Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA) following the "Registration
				Procedures for Message Header Fields" <xref target="RFC3864">RFC 3864</xref>.
				[TO BE REMOVED: This
				registration should take place at the following location:
				http://www.iana.org/assignments/message-headers/message-headers.xhtml]
				Further, it defines a parameter for the "Link" header. There is no registry
				for link-param except for the values listed in <xref target="RFC5988">[RFC5988]</xref>
				so the parameter "profile" will be seen as a link-extension.</t>
			<section title="Accept-Profile HTTP Header Registration" anchor="iana-accept-profile">
				<t>The Accept-Profile header should be added to the permanent
					registry of message header fields (see <xref target="RFC3864">RFC 3864</xref>), taking into
					account the guidelines given by HTTP/1.1 <xref target="RFC7231">RFC 7231</xref>".</t>

				<t>Header Field Name: Accept-Profile</t>

				<t>Applicable Protocol: Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP)</t>

				<t>Status: Standard</t>

				<t>Author/Change controller: IETF</t>

				<t>Specification document(s): RFC XXXX</t>

			</section>
			<section title="Profile HTTP Header Registration" anchor="iana-profile">
				<t>The Profile header should be added to the permanent
					registry of message header fields (see <xref target="RFC3864">RFC 3864</xref>), taking into
					account the guidelines given by HTTP/1.1 <xref target="RFC7231">RFC 7231</xref>".</t>

				<t>Header Field Name: Profile</t>

				<t>Applicable Protocol: Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP)</t>

				<t>Status: Standard</t>

				<t>Author/Change controller: IETF</t>

				<t>Specification document(s): RFC XXXX</t>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
			<t>The Accept-Profile and Profile headers may expose information that a
				User Agent or an origin server would
				prefer to not publish. In such a case, a server can simply stop
				exposing the header, in which case HTTP interactions would be back to
				the level of standard HTTP (i.e., with no indication what profiles the
				UA or the server prefer and/or can handle.</t>
		</section>
	</middle>

	<back>
		<references title="Normative References">
			&RFC2119;
			&RFC5234;
			&RFC7230;
			&RFC7231;
		</references>

		<references title="Informative References">
			&RFC3236;
			&RFC3870;
			&RFC3864;
			&RFC5988;
			&RFC6906;
			&RFC7240;
			<reference anchor="DSP" target="http://dublincore.org/documents/dc-dsp/">
				<front>
					<title>Description Set Profiles: A constraint language for Dublin Core Application Profiles</title>

					<author initials="M." surname="Nilsson">
						<organization>KTH</organization>
					</author>

					<date year="2008" />
				</front>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="IANAMEDIAREG"
					target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/">
				<front>
					<title>Media Types</title>

					<author>
						<organization>IANA</organization>
					</author>

					<date year="2015" />
				</front>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="JSONLD"
					target="http://www.w3.org/TR/json-ld/">
				<front>
					<title>JSON-LD 1.0: A JSON-based Serialization for Linked Data</title>

					<author initials="M." surname="Sporny">
						<organization>Digital Bazaar</organization>
					</author>
					<author initials="G." surname="Kellogg">
						<organization>Kellogg Associates</organization>
					</author>
					<author initials="M." surname="Lanthaler">
						<organization>Graz University of Technology</organization>
					</author>

					<date year="2015" />
				</front>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="rachelandheery" target="http://www.ariadne.ac.uk/issue25/app-profiles">
				<front>
					<title>Application Profiles: Mixing and Matching Metadata Schemas</title>
					<author initials="R." surname="Heery">
						<organization>UK Office for Library and Information networking (UKOLN), University of Bath</organization>
					</author>
					<author initials="M." surname="Patel">
						<organization>UK Office for Library and Information networking (UKOLN), University of Bath</organization>
					</author>
					<date year="2000"/>
				</front>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="SHACL" target="http://www.w3.org/TR/shacl/">
				<front>
					<title>Shapes Constraint Language (SHACL): W3C First Public Working Draft 08 October 2015</title>

					<author initials="H." surname="Knublauch">
						<organization>TopQuadrant, Inc.</organization>
					</author>
					<author initials="A." surname="Ryman">
						<organization/>
					</author>

					<date year="2014" />
				</front>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="TURTLE" target="http://www.w3.org/TR/turtle/">
				<front>
					<title>RDF 1.1 Turtle</title>

					<author initials="E." surname="Prud'hommeaux">
						<organization>W3C</organization>
					</author>
					<author initials="G." surname="Carothers">
						<organization>Lex Machina, Inc.</organization>
					</author>

					<date year="2014" />
				</front>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="XSD" target="http://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-1/">
				<front>
					<title>XML Schema Part 1: Structures Second Edition</title>

					<author initials="H. S." surname="Thompson">
						<organization>University of Edinburgh</organization>
					</author>
					<author initials="D." surname="Beech">
						<organization>Oracle Corporation</organization>
					</author>
					<author initials="M." surname="Maloney">
						<organization>Commerce One</organization>
					</author>
					<author initials="N." surname="Mendelsohn">
						<organization>Lotus Development Corporation</organization>
					</author>

					<date year="2004" />
				</front>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="XMLBEANS" target="https://xmlbeans.apache.org/">
				<front>
					<title>XMLBeans</title>

					<author>
						<organization>Apache Software Foundation</organization>
					</author>

					<date year="2014" />
				</front>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="XMLSCHEMA" target="https://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema11-1/">
				<front>
					<title>W3C XML Schema Definition Language (XSD) 1.1 Part 1: Structures</title>
					<author initials="S." surname="Gao">
						<organization>IBM</organization>
					</author>
					<author initials="C. M." surname="Sperberg-McQueen">
						<organization>Black Mesa Technologies LLC</organization>
					</author>
					<author initials="H. S." surname="Thompson">
						<organization>University of Edinburgh</organization>
					</author>
					<date year="2012"/>
				</front>
			</reference>
		</references>
	</back>
</rfc>

